got a call from an American journalist
who said that he had a source who said
that [music] I had tortured Abuza.
President Bush said that if there was
torture, it was the result of a rogue
CIA officer and then nobody said
anything. I kept waiting for it to go
public. Number one, the CIA was
torturing its prisoners. Number two,
that torture was official US government
policy. it was not the result of a
rogue. And number three, that the policy
had been approved by the president
himself. The day after I blew the
whistle on the torture [music] program,
a former deputy director of the CIA sent
me an email
and he said, "You've chosen a difficult
road,
but I'm glad somebody did it. I believe
that torture was a criminal act and so
revealing it was an act of patriotism,
not an act of criminality.
As far as the CIA goes, I'm on record as
saying I don't believe there should be a
CIA. I think it's a force for evil.
My very first week, my boss said, "Come
up with a standard operating procedure
for taking down an al-Qaeda safe house."
Of course, we had something called high
value targets, HBTs. And that was the
the obvious list. It was it was bin
Laden, Zawahi, Abu Zuba, Khalik
Muhammad, Ramsey, Benes, the usual cast
of [music] characters. And those people
who were that cooperative would remain
in ISI custody. We [music] believed at
the time that Abuazuba was the number
three in al-Qaeda. He was not.
>> Did you feel comfortable with the
techniques?
>> Uh, frankly, no. And I elected to uh to
forgo the training. I was asked if I
wanted to be trained in the enhanced
techniques [music] and I sought the
counsel of a senior agency officer who's
still an agency officer and I said,
"What would you do in my situation?" And
he said, "Frankly, I think it's a
slippery slope. An accident's going to
happen and uh I wouldn't do it." I
thought that somebody was going to make
it public because once they started
torturing him, we started getting cables
back, reports back from the secret site.
I was at headquarters and they were
saying, "This is terrible. This is
illegal. This is not what I signed up
for. I quit. I'm coming home. I can't
believe we're doing this. I'm going to
call the FBI." And I thought, "Oh, thank
God. It's not just me. Other people at
the CIA realized this is a criminal
act." And then nobody said anything. I
kept waiting for it to go public. Then I
left the CIA in 2004, early 2004, and
still waited for somebody to say
something. Somebody blew the whistle on
the secret prisons. Somebody else blew
the whistle on the rendition program.
And I thought, okay, this is good. These
were criminal acts as well. Somebody's
going to say something about Abu Zubeda.
nothing.
And then in December of 2007, I got a
call from an American journalist who
said that he had a source who said that
I had tortured Abu Zubeda. I said that
was absolutely untrue. I was the only
person who was kind to Abu Zubeda. But
then a couple of days later, President
Bush said that if there was torture, it
was the result of a rogue CIA officer.
And I said to my wife, who was also in
the CIA,
I said, "They're going to try to pin
this on me because I was the only one
who objected internally through the
chain of command." So I called the
journalist and I said, "I will give you
your interview." And I decided that no
matter what he asked me, I was going to
tell the truth. And so I said three
things. Number one, the CIA was
torturing its prisoners. Number two,
that torture was official US government
policy. It was not the result of a
rogue. And number three, that the policy
had been approved by the president
himself.
And then everything
spun out of control after that.
My overall belief for many many years
up until
up until the torture of Abu Zubeda was
that we are the good guys, right? We're
the good guys. We're the freedom
fighters.
And then I realized
we're not the good guys.
We're no better than the bad guys. The
things that we criticize other countries
for, we were doing every day at secret
sites around the world. Let me give you
an example.
When I was serving in Bahrain, I
mentioned that I was on rotation. I was
on on assignment to the State Department
and as part of that assignment, I was
the embassy's human rights officer.
There was a an inifada in Bahrain at the
time and a lot of people were were shot
and killed by [music] the police or were
arrested and then never charged with a
crime, just held in communicado in
prison. And um I would go to
the minister of interior and say, "Your
highness, you you can't just shoot a
15year-old boy because he marched in a
pro-democracy demonstration. I have to
report that to Congress, right? Right?
And it might affect arm sales. You can't
just kill people just because you don't
like their politics. But then what
happens when a human rights officer
makes a complaint like that and then
later in the day a CIA station chief
goes in to see the same minister and say
and says, "Don't don't listen to the
human rights guy.
We want you to open a secret prison here
where we can bring prisoners to be
tortured and we'll share the
intelligence with you. Who's he going to
listen to? He's going to listen to to me
or he's going to listen to the guy with
with the suitcases full of money. So I I
realized
on October I'm sorry on August the 2nd,
2002, I realized we are the bad guys.
You know, we talk about human rights and
civil rights and civil liberties and
rule of law and it's like a joke.
I did not think I'd get arrested because
we have a law in the United States that
says that it is illegal to classify a
criminal act for the purpose of keeping
it from the American people. I believed
that torture was a criminal act. And so
revealing it was an act of patriotism,
not an act of criminality.
And to tell you the truth, I wasn't
arrested for revealing the torture
program. They found a way around it uh
to arrest me for something else, but
originally they charged me with three
counts of espionage
and they had to drop those charges. I
hadn't committed espionage. And so it
was this legal cat and mouse game that
we played for the next uh four or five
years, four years until they finally
arrested me.
[music]
You know, a lot of whistleblowers commit
suicide
uh because the pressure is so great. I
was facing 45 years in prison with the
original charges. [music] 45 years in
prison. One of the prosecutors told me
that I was going to die in prison and
that I would never meet my
grandchildren. But then at the same
time,
my wife, [music] now my ex-wife,
um she said, "You have to embrace this.
You didn't do anything wrong, and so you
have to keep talking about it because
your side of the story needs to become
the side of record."
And so she was right. and I began
talking about it to every media outlet
in the world that asked for an
interview. I never said no. And she was
right in that they eventually moved on
to their next target which was Edward
Snowden and uh and then Julian Assange.
And so my side of the story has become
the side of record. Another thing too,
and this is something that I didn't
appreciate at the time because I felt
like the entire weight of the American
government had fallen on my head, but my
most
senior detractors, the CIA officials who
wanted me dead or wanted me to die in
prison, eventually they died
and they're just not around anymore. and
this new generation of CIA officers,
many of them have reached out to me as
recently as two weeks ago to say that I
did the right thing and that they still
talk about me at the CIA 20 years after
I've left saying that I did the right
thing. So, you know, in the end, it's
all worth it. I'll add one thing, too.
Um,
the day after I blew the whistle on the
torture program, a former deputy
director of the CIA sent me an email
and he said, "You've chosen a difficult
road,
but I'm [music] glad somebody did it,
and I wish that I had had the courage
for it to be me."
That meant a lot to me. A lot.
It made me realize that it was worth it.
[music]
My lawyers told me there was probably no
way I would get out of it without prison
time, but I only ended up getting 23
months. It was actually a relief. As odd
as that might sound, it was a relief
because there was an end date to it. I
knew that this nightmare was going to be
over in 23 months. I met a community in
the prison that that took care of me and
protected me and um I made a lifelong
friend in prison. And uh you know, this
could have been such a far worse
experience. The the Justice Department
thought that they would break me. They
thought that they were ruin they would
ruin me. And all they did was they
energized me and they gave me a cause. A
cause for the rest of my life.
How the CIA taught me to survive and
thrive in prison. And I start off, it's
kind of like semi humorous, but I start
off with 20 lessons that I learned at
the CIA and how [music] I implemented
those 20 lessons in daily prison life.
Never underestimate your mental
toughness was one that people can take a
lot more stress and abuse than they
realize they can take. Another one was
kind of a joke at the CIA. was admit
nothing, deny everything, make counter
accusations.
And in my dealings with the guards, I
used that all the time. It was very
frustrating for them, but I never told
them anything.
Another was get others to do your dirty
work.
That way, you're always clean.
That was a valuable lesson in prison.
And like I said, there are 20 of those.
Some of them are tongue and cheek. Some
of them are very serious.
[music]
From my own perspective, there's one
philosophical lesson and there's one
practical lesson. The philosophical
lesson is know the truth and the truth
shall set you free. The the truth is
should always be paramount even when the
truth is painful. We always have to know
the truth and to tell the truth. From a
practical perspective, I would advise
anybody, no matter where you are in the
world, if you are considering blowing
the whistle on waste, fraud, abuse,
illegality, or threats to the public
health or public safety, which is the
international definition of
whistleblowing,
hire a lawyer first
and have that lawyer sitting next to you
when you blew the whistle.
As far as the CIA goes, I'm on record as
saying I don't believe there should be a
CIA. I think it's a force for evil. But
if there has to be a CIA,
then it's up to the American government
and especially the congressional
oversight committees to absolutely
ensure that the CIA respects the rule of
law and respects human rights and human
dignity. And we're still not there yet.
And also, I feel like I owe so many of
these men an apology for what my
government did to them. You know, in the
darkness, in the shadows, outside the
rule of law, they deserve an apology.
They deserve compensation, which they'll
never get,
but at the very least, they deserve an
apology.
[music] worldwide.
Uh the job of intelligence agencies,
very simply, is to recruit spies to
steal secrets. It's really that simple.
And uh I think the most immediate issues
are secrets pertaining to terrorism
because we're all affected by terrorism.
Um
at the same time, this is not unique to
the United States. I'm talking about
every intelligence [music] service in
the world. Citizens of every country
should remind themselves that these
intelligence services and intelligence
officers work for us. We are the
taxpayers. They are working in the
public service and so they should be
subject to appropriate oversight. It
should be up to every government and
every legislature to make sure that
their secret services are not violating
basic humanitarian laws.
I think that most of us fail. Um, most
countries fail in that respect.
Certainly here in the United States, we
have failed many, many, many times over
the decades. But we should constantly
keep pressure on our governments to keep
pressure on our intelligence services to
respect the rule of law.
And there are a lot of people who um
have mental breakdowns because of the
pressures associated with this work. You
know, it's funny.
I'll tell you something personal about
myself.
Uh many of my colleagues suffered from
PTSD, post-traumatic stress disorder,
and I never did.
It never affected me. I don't know how
or why, but I was able to separate the
danger, the risk of the job with my
personal life. It was only when I got
divorced that I got PTSD
because of the divorce. And I went to
see a doctor, a doctor who I knew from
the CIA, and he said, "You know, it's
amazing to me that you came back from
Islamabad and you had no signs of PTSD."
I said I loved Islamabad. I loved the
job. I loved the work, the operations,
the people. It was like a vacation for
me. I loved it.
But the breakup of my marriage, I never
saw that coming.
So for a lot of people,
you know, there's turnover because a lot
of people literally they lose their
minds doing some of these things.
They try to weed those people out in the
application process. If you're mentally
fragile, you're not going to you're not
going to cut out be cut out for a CIA
job. But sometimes it's just too much.
And so you have to
you have to be able to recognize when
you [music] are when your mental health
is in danger and you have to be willing
to act on it to protect yourself because
the CIA doesn't care if you have a
mental breakdown. You have to care if
you're having a mental breakdown. The
CIA doesn't care if you get better. They
just want you to get better enough so
they can send you back overseas to do
more work. So, you really have to worry
about yourself. That's that's the advice
I would give.